<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Tom's Blog</title>
    <link>https://www.tomdooner.com</link>
    <description>Hello, I'm Tom Dooner and this is my blog.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>2017-11-07T08:00:00+00:00</lastBuildDate>
    <ttl>240</ttl>
    <item>
      <title>Brigade Congress Recap 2017</title>
      <link>https://www.tomdooner.com/2017/11/07/brigade-congress.html</link>
      <author>tomdooner@gmail.com</author>
      <pubDate>2017-11-07T08:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
      <category>updates</category>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month, roughly 200 technologists of all backgrounds, locations, and occupations came together to discuss how to build the next version of the Code for America (CfA) Brigade network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/2017/cfa-brigade-logo.png" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How we can build a government that works for the people, by the people, in the 21st century? Representatives from local Brigades across the country came together in Philadelphia to answer this question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-brigade-network"&gt;What is the Brigade network?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Brigade program has been around for a long time. As one of the first CfA programs dating back to 2012, it's built around the idea that in order to improve government for Americans, we have to start close to home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are amazing folks who dedicate their week nights and free time to working on projects for residents of their cities. On a single night, civic technologists might work on projects that run the gamut from helping people understand how their government works to visualizing complex data to helping residents interact more easily with government services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in a time governments must be digitally capable, and the local Brigade is what makes that possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="brigade-history"&gt;Brigade History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backdrop for the Brigade Congress meeting, though, was not all sunshine and rainbows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, CfA &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://civichall.org/civicist/recharging-the-brigade-code-for-americas-challenge/"&gt;resdesigned the Brigade program&lt;/a&gt; into a format which required more sustainability on the part of Brigades. By distancing them from the top-level organization's day-to-day, this meant that fiscal sponsorship from CfA itself would be wound down and Brigades would need to heavily invest in fundraising. Many brigades struggled to accomplish this, resulting in leadership burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, CfA has been working to improve relations with Brigades and help them be more successful. First, by embarking on an ambitious network-wide &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/17fp1uRTWjIQWmlJmGFYMJ85uY2XCOZIZGh_YAMqC0zQ/edit#slide=id.g165d5bc4f9_1_258"&gt;research and co-creation process&lt;/a&gt;, Brigade leaders throughout the country gave ideas on governance structures and areas of improvement for CfA. (For example, streamlining the reimbursement process for expenditures. I think most Brigade leaders would say it has improved since then!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A concrete outcome of the process is the Brigade &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://medium.com/code-for-america/national-advisory-council-election-results-and-next-steps-54c53ece6ae2"&gt;National Advisory Council (NAC)&lt;/a&gt;, a group of leaders elected by the network to be the official representatives of the geographically diverse network in conversations with CfA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that's not all. More recently, CfA has doubled-down on building a great "Network team" at CfA. (More about that in a couple days.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is with this backdrop that the NAC was positioned to suggest CfA hosting the first ever Brigade Congress–a two day unconference exculsively for and by the Brigade network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="openoakland-representing"&gt;OpenOakland representing!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/2017/brigade-congress-openoakland.jpg" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From left: Joanna, me, Ramy, Helen, and Howard.
Not pictured: Neil, Mike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm proud to have been able to represent both OpenOakland &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Code for America! Although the timing of the event was right as my CfA fellowship was wrapping up, as one of OpenOakland's Hack Night Leads and a member of almost four years at this point, I felt it especially important to attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, OpenOakland was well-represented!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="to-the-unconference"&gt;To the Unconference!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what was the event actually like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, first, we all met at a datacenter for a reception. What the venue lacked in acoustics, it more than made up for in symbolism. What better location to kick off a meeting of civic technologists from across the nation than a couple floors above where the fiber cables connect our physical communication fabric together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/codeforamerica/status/918972114954317825&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the reception, it was back to the hotel for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="official-kickoff"&gt;Official Kickoff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the main conference room, the events started off with some introductions followed by lightning talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/jhibbets/status/919551051644264448&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In true unconference style, we got to dot voting on session topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/SFbrigade/status/919204329231388672&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the sessions that were planned&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/Ryan_Koch/status/919574191623557120&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/City_Sostenible/status/919583358375645184&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="key-takeaways"&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across many sessions and conversations that happened throughout the weekend, a few themes kept recurring – Brigades from small to large face many of the same challenges. Broadly, I think these boil down into two categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structural&lt;/strong&gt; - What is the role of the Brigade in the community? What types of project make sense to deploy/redeploy? How do we make sure that our diverse communities are represented in our organizations?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tactical&lt;/strong&gt; - How can Brigades improve retention? How to build a sustainable organization when leadership changes? How to make sure that members are empowered to build projects in a way that is aligned with the organization and can be maintained?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Brigades are focused inward. OpenOakland is focused on OpenOakland, and so forth, and this is probably as it should be. However, it makes us lose touch with the broader network and miss best practices from elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sharing-projects-between-brigades"&gt;Sharing Projects between Brigades&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This came up more than once at Congress. How can we take a success in one place and redeploy it somewhere else that has the same challenges?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I think of this topic, I can't get Courtbot out of my mind. Originally written by CfA fellows in Atlanta to help residents remember their court dates, it is getting new a life in Tulsa. Its promise only begins there, however. In order to fulfill the mission of Clientcomm, we need court schedule information, and Courtbot is our community-created moonshot at surfacing this information in a structured way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Courtbot is only the first step. There are excellent projects like &lt;a target="_blank" href="http://mapsfor.us"&gt;mapsfor.us&lt;/a&gt; (Code for Atlanta) and the Homelessness Portal (Code for San Jose) that hold incredible potential to provide value across jurisdictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sharing-best-practices"&gt;Sharing Best Practices&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of discussion around sharing best practices for organizing. Here are a couple topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diversity and inclusion. How can we do it, and do it now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/TechnicallyPHL/status/919619676975529985&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/c_sethna/status/919213402584637441&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we engage city partners&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/Ryan_Koch/status/919250944675799040&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools to use (like journey maps) via Code for Orlando's &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ErinFonziDenton"&gt;@ErinFonziDenton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/codeforamerica/status/919266564892971008&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/Ryan_Koch/status/919266578641965062&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="in-summary"&gt;In Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brigade Congress was a great event, and a great opportunity for us in Brigades to align around a common cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/SFbrigade/status/919613849120182272&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, and all the connections coming out of the event, the network has never been poised for more success. Let's keep up the momentum, work together, and make our governments work for the people!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beginnings</title>
      <link>https://www.tomdooner.com/2017/01/31/beginnings.html</link>
      <author>tomdooner@gmail.com</author>
      <pubDate>2017-01-31T08:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
      <category>updates</category>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow, I begin my next adventure: a 9-month fellowship with &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.codeforamerica.org"&gt;Code for America&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll be working with Multnomah County, Oregon (which includes Portland) to implement &lt;a target="_blank" href="http://github.com/slco-2016/clientcomm"&gt;a web app&lt;/a&gt; that facilitates communication between victims of crime and case workers that are helping them apply for assistance from the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victims assistance programs are important to help victims pay for medical bills, funerals, mental health consuling, and other expenses. This helps victims get back to a semblance of normalcy so they don't have to turn to crime or drugs. (California spends &lt;a target="_blank" href="http://vcgcb.ca.gov/victims/statistics/fy12-13.aspx"&gt;$62M&lt;/a&gt; annually, Oregon spends &lt;a target="_blank" href="http://www.doj.state.or.us/about/pdf/15-17_doj_lab_agency_summary.pdf"&gt;$60M&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="becoming-more-political"&gt;Becoming more political&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of unfortunate stuff happening in America right now. Xenophobia, threats to healthcare, and questionable leadership all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my two years at Brigade, I hoped that our product would facilitate a better political climate, and this would spare me from an oblication to be politically involved outside of work. It's now becoming evident to me that &lt;strong&gt;this is not enough&lt;/strong&gt;. Creating a platform and hoping for the best isn't going to help actual people, right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem is, &lt;em&gt;I don't know the best way I can help people&lt;/em&gt;. Hopefully, something will come of the gigantic national movements, but helping on that scale is daunting. &lt;em&gt;City&lt;/em&gt; government, however, seems like a great scale: a large impact on residents' lives with less bureaucracy. This scale is part of what made me apply for the fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toward-the-future"&gt;Toward the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm approaching this new opportunity as my chance to become more politically engaged and hopefully use my skills to make a difference in peoples' lives. Even if it's only be a handful in Portland, you've gotta start somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if this is inspiring to you, &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://www.codeforamerica.org/join-us/join-our-team"&gt;Code for America is hiring&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smarter, Relevant Chef Tests</title>
      <link>https://www.tomdooner.com/2014/12/01/smarter-relevant-chef-tests.html</link>
      <author>tomdooner@gmail.com</author>
      <pubDate>2014-12-01T08:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
      <category>technology</category>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Save hours on every commit with chef-relevant-tests. This new gem will find only
your most-likely-to-have-been-affected Chef tests.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on 2014 EDGE Conference</title>
      <link>https://www.tomdooner.com/2014/09/20/notes-on-edge-2014.html</link>
      <author>tomdooner@gmail.com</author>
      <pubDate>2014-09-20T07:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
      <category>technology</category>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 20th, I had the pleasure of attending the EDGE conference hosted
by FT at Adobe's headquarters. Here are some notes I took from the many excellent
sessions about web standards development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="installable-apps-and-permissions"&gt;Installable Apps and Permissions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web has had a rough history of attempts at offline apps. Part of this is due
to the lack of a design language on web. Even simple things like specifying an app
name or icon are not standardized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/KfJfDNy_S5M" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an option on iOS to use &lt;code&gt;apple-mobile-web-app&lt;/code&gt; &amp;lt;meta&amp;gt; tag, however it's usage is infrequent and is broken in many ways. There is some debate about the approach the web should take&amp;amp;emdash;a guy from PhoneGap said "I don't think we should spend time making an abstraction that compiles to native UIs."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, app permissions is a big unsolved question. There are two broad categories of permissions that the user could grant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security Questions (where software can make an opinionated decision for the user)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Privacy Questions (where the user is responsible more directly for their own fate)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates complexity in attempts at a unified permissions model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="layout-performance"&gt;Layout Performance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android + iOS are built for a single reason: apps. The web is built for a very different one: documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pi0UEgH9eA8?list=PLOU2XLYxmsIIlUmhjsPyZ6LIZbu0EzNoN" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can't have it both ways, what is the primary use case of the web?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need better layout benchmarks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After GPU improvements dry up, then where will we get our next 10x
improvement in performance? We don't see the answer to that yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="security--identity-mostly-security"&gt;Security &amp;amp; Identity (mostly Security)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STARTTLS usage for SMTP is still increasing in adoption quickly
Soon, Certificate Transparency will be required for all EV certificates.
What is the future of the password?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OaqzLn4-pxk?list=PLOU2XLYxmsIIlUmhjsPyZ6LIZbu0EzNoN" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id="web-standards--extensible-web-manifesto"&gt;Web Standards &amp;amp; Extensible Web Manifesto&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tying to iterate on the web quickly is hard, and the "Extensible Web Manifesto" is a way to tackle this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vl4q0Q9ucIs?list=PLOU2XLYxmsIIlUmhjsPyZ6LIZbu0EzNoN" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the gist is that we should embrace the polyfill and vendors building experimental features. Over time we will find out what works and then standardize based on an existing implementation. Browsers should be liberal in what they accept in case a different vendor decides to invent new properties.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Availability Sidekiq with Redis Sentinel</title>
      <link>https://www.tomdooner.com/2014/08/29/high-availability-sidekiq.html</link>
      <author>tomdooner@gmail.com</author>
      <pubDate>2014-08-29T07:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
      <category>technology</category>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Setting up a Sidekiq queue tolerant of Redis failure has never been easier. This
post will help you get your Ruby application connecting properly so you can reap
the uptime benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Webpack in the Rails Asset Pipeline</title>
      <link>https://www.tomdooner.com/2014/06/29/webpack.html</link>
      <author>tomdooner@gmail.com</author>
      <pubDate>2014-06-29T07:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
      <category>technology</category>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rails applications have long had a unilateral asset compilation strategy
provided by Sprockets (as a part of &lt;a target="_blank" href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/asset_pipeline.html"&gt;Ruby on Rails's Asset
Pipeline&lt;/a&gt;).  However, as the depth of JavaScript
&lt;a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/jrburke/requirejs"&gt;build&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/gruntjs/grunt"&gt;tools&lt;/a&gt; increases, application authors can and should
take advantage of more diverse asset combination techniques than what Sprockets
is designed to provide. This can lead to better long-term maintainability
through modularity of frontend components (which is &lt;a target="_blank" href="http://www.polymer-project.org/"&gt;all the rage&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a target="_blank" href="http://facebook.github.io/react/"&gt;these days&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Brigade, we wanted to integrate the &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/webpack/webpack"&gt;Webpack module bundler&lt;/a&gt; to
combine our CommonJS modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we also wanted to keep the Sprockets as the last step in our build
pipeline for the easy integration with Rails via the &lt;code&gt;asset_path&lt;/code&gt; helpers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up creating a prerequisite step in the asset precompilation process by
using a bit of Rake trickery. It has been working pretty well for us, and
perhaps you will find it useful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class="highlighted-code ruby"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# lib/tasks/assets.rake&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# The webpack task must run before assets:environment task.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Otherwise Sprockets cannot find the files that webpack produces.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="no"&gt;Rake&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'assets:precompile'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;clear_prerequisites&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;enhance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'assets:compile_environment'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:assets&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# In this task, set prerequisites for the assets:precompile task&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;task&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:compile_environment&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:webpack&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="no"&gt;Rake&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'assets:environment'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;invoke&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="n"&gt;desc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'Compile assets with webpack'&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;task&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:webpack&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;sh&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'$(npm bin)/webpack --config webpack.config.js'&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="n"&gt;task&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:clobber&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;rm_rf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;root&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;/app/assets/javascripts/{bundle.js,components.js}"&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
